Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
Robert E. Lee Papers
Inclusive 1792-1935
1833-1870
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
WLU.Coll.0064
24 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Online Access
View materials from this collection online via W & L's Digital Archive
Scope and Contents
This collection contains primary and secondary resources pertaining to Robert E. Lee and the Lee family. Included are correspondences from, to, and about Lee and various family members; memorabilia, pamphlets, photographs, reminiscences, miscellaneous personal papers, family history and genealogy. The collection includes materials acquired from the Lee family and items donated to and purchased and compiled by W&L University since Lee's tenure as president of Washington College from 1865 - 1870. Adminstrative papers, such as President's Reports, etc..., from Robert E. Lee's presidency of the school may be found within the W&L University Archives. Please contact W&L Special Collections for information regarding the University Archives.
Printed ephemera; Photographs; Military orders; Correspondence; Virginia -- Lexington; Postwar reconstruction; University purchasing; United States -- Confederate States of America; Administration; University autonomy; University towns; Virginia; Virginia--Arlington; Civil war; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Printed ephemera; Pamphlets; Arlington House, the Robert E. Lee Memorial (Va.) -- Robert E. Lee; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Confederate States of America. Army of Northern Virginia; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) -- Robert E. Lee
- Secure Cabinet Items
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to William McCloud Bowe, 1863-04-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter from Robert E. Lee to William McCloud Bowe dated April 18, 1863 rejecting a request for furlough from the army. The letter was likely dictated but is signed by Lee.
    Bowe, William McCloud
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Edward Turner, 1861-09-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    Letter from Robert E. Lee to Edward Turner about the death of Col. J. A. Washington (John Augustine Washington) at Valley River, dated 14 September 14, 1861
    Washington, John Augustine, 1821 - 1861; Turner, Edward
  - Special Order 56, Army of Northern Virginia, 1864-02-27; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Taylor, Walter H.
    In Special Order 56, Army of Northern Virginia, which is dated Feb 27, 1864, Lee decrees the end of Lieutenant Granville Gray's career stating that he is now living in the lunatic asylum in Staunton, Va. The document was written in Staunton. It is signed by Walter H. Taylor.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of John F. Foster in 2006
    Mental illness; Gray, Granville, Lieutenant
  - General Orders No. 9, 1865-04-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    Robert E. Lee's last order as commander of the Army of Northern Virginia. This copy is written and signed by Lee.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee accepting presidency of Washington College, 1865-08-24; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    In this letter Robert E. Lee writes to the Board of Trustess of Washington College accepting the presidency of the institution.
    Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Col. Charles Marshall, 1866-01-19; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    This letter contains information about the furniture that Charles Marshall is purchasing for Lee in Baltimore.
    Purchase from Stuart Lutz Historic Documents Inc.
    Marshall, Charles
  - From Robert E. Lee to Rathmell Wilson, 1866-07-02; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    In this letter Lee writes to Rathmell Wilson in Philadelphia that the Washington College Board of Trustees has elected to let him purchase books for the institution.
    Gift of the estate of Mary Margaret Johnson.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to John Lyle Campbell, 1867-09-09; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    In this letter written from Sweet Springs Robert E. Lee writies that due to his health he won't be returning to the college right away. He asks all the faculty to help the students prepare for classes. A transcription is housed with this letter.
    Campbell, J. L. (John Lyle)
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Mr. V. M. Root, 1870-01-20; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item is glued to cardstock.
    In this letter Lee gives a prospective student advice on the choosing which state institution of higher to attend.
    Root, V. M.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to John Lyle Campbell, 1870-08-03; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item has been silked.
    In this letter Lee writes to Campbell, who had recently been asked to be Superintent of the Rockbridge County Schools, that he does not think accepting this position would greatly impact his duties at Washington College.
  - Robert E. Lee's Oath of Office for Washington College, 1865-10-02; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item has been barrowed and encapsulated.
    This document is Robert E. Lee's signed Oath of office as President of Washington College. It is signed William White.
    White, William S. (William Spotswood)
  - Excuse by Robert E. Lee for W. H. Kinckle, 1869-03-26; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item is glued to a card. A photocopy of the back of the card is housed with the original.
    Written excuse by Robert E. Lee for William H. Kinckle to go to church on Good Friday and miss his recitation as a result.
    Good Friday; Kinckle, William H.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Ms. Caroline C. Stuart, 1868-07-04; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item has been barrowed.
    In this letter Robert E. Lee talks his wife's health and making trips to Hot Springs and Warm Springs. He also mentions his two daughters Agnes and Mildred. He makes mentions of rumors that George Washington Custis Lee recently got engaged.
    Purchased from Stuart Lutz Historical Documents Inc.
    Stuart, Caroline
  - General Orders No. 3, 1865-02-06
    This order by Adjutant General and Inspector General of the Confederate Army, Samuel Cooper, raises Robert E. Lee to General in Chief of the Armies of the Confederacy.
  - Letter to the Students of Washington College, 1869-03-30; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    In this letter Robert E. Lee writes to the students about the effects of their disruptive behavior on the town and asks them to minimize that behavior during the upcoming April Fools Day parade. A transcription of the letter is housed with the original item.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Walter H. Galt, 1869-10-15; This item is encapsulated with the original envelope.
    In this letter Lee thanks Walter H. Galt, who established Galt Jewelers in Washington, DC, for a color photograph of George Washington Parke Custis.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Stilson Hutchins, 1869-08-06; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    Purchased from Stuart Lutz Historical Documents.
    This letter from Robert E. Lee to Stilson Hutchins, founder of the Washington Post, thanks him for copies of the St. Louis Times, which contained an article on Washington College.
  - Letter from a student to Washington College faculty signed by Robert E. Lee, 1869-12-21; Waddill, Frank A. (Frank Alexander); Item is glued to a piece of board.
    Letter from Frank A. Waddill, Class of 1870, to the faculty requesting permission for five days off from school. Note on the back of the board to which the letter is glued: 'Frank A. Waddill was a classmate (roomate?) of Wilmer H. Shields at Washington College (and then Washington and Lee University)...'
    Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Blair Robertson
    In this letter Lee writes to Blair Robertson returning the pet chicken, which was originally a gift from Robertson, to its orginal owner for safe keeping. Lee feels that harm may come to the chicken as the military is moving camp.
  - Leaf from the first Washington College catalogue
    Leaf from first Washington College catalogue, which was printed before Lee was official invested as college president in October 1865. He is listed as the President and a Professor of Mental and Moral Science, Lee but never actually taught at the college.
  - Letter from Mary Custis Lee to unknown, 1864
    In this letter Mary Custis Lee writes to an unknown correspondentabout her ailments, travel, General Grant's movements through VA, and inflation. The letter was written from Richmond in 1864.
  - Photograph of Robert E. Lee in floppy tie, This item is encapsulated
    This photograph is of Robert E. Lee with his floppy tie. The inscription on back says 'for my young friend John Opie from Mary Custis Lee'.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, 1861
    Lee writes to Louisa upon the death of her father, John Augustine Washington, who was killed in battle during the American Civil War.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, 1862
    In this letter Robert E. Lee writes to Louisa about the last letter ever written by her father John Augustine Washington.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, Undated
    In this letter Robert E. Lee asks Louise when he can see her and invites her to visit his military camp.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, 1863; This item is housed in the Secure Cabinet.
    In this letter Lee writes to Louisa about arrangements for the family to received her father's (John Augustine Washington) personal papers. He notes that John was the last proprietor of Mount Vernon of the family of Washington.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, 1863
    In this letter Lee writes to Louisa about her cousin Charles Alexander who was taken by the Union military as a prisoner of war. He writes that he has made a request for Alexander's release.
  - Letter from Robert E. Lee to Miss Louisa Washington, 1868
    In this letter Lee writes to Louisa about suggestions for what to inscribe on her father's (John Augustine Washington) tombstone.
  - Robert E. Lee's will, 1846-08-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); This item is barrowed.
    This document is Robert E. Lee's last will and testament. There is also a note on back of will from November 7, 1870.
- Letters from Robert E. Lee, 1833-1870 (Box 1-4B)
  - Letters from Robert E. Lee, 1833-1862 (Box 1)
    - Control Folder (Box 1, Folder 0)
    - Robert E. Lee to Mr. Campbell Esq., 1834-12-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Note from Robert E. Lee regarding the salaries of clerks in his office. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Robert E. Lee to John Mackay, 1833-01-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter regarding Fanny Kemble and other matters. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      General
      A photostat copy of letter. Original possibly located at Georgia Historical Society. Please contact them for conditions governing use.
      Mackay, John; Kemble, Fanny
    - Robert E. Lee to Captain W. A. Eliason, 1837-04-11; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter regarding a contract for the construction of a steam boat and engine. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Eliason, W. A., Captain
    - Robert E. Lee to "Squire" Cullum, 1837-05-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Writing from Washington D.C., Robert E. Lee writes of social matters. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Robert E. Lee to F. N. Barbarin Esq., 1844-05-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter to a friend or colleague regarding possible travel plans and Robert E. Lee's search for a new job. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Robert E. Lee to Lieutenant G. T. Beauregard, 1845-02-13; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter acknowledging engineering departnment account receipts. Assume G. T. Beauregard is Pierre Gustave Toutant Beauregard. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant)
    - Robert E. Lee to George Washington Custis Lee, 1845-12-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Transcribes note from William H.F. Lee to Custis Lee, then discusses Christmas presents and inquires about his studies. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      A facsimile copy. The location of the original letter is unknown.
      Lee, George Washington Custis; Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh
    - Robert E. Lee to Julia Gratiot, 1845-11-27; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Note regarding Robert E. Lee's inability to attend his niece's wedding and recalls other memories with her. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes a letter and a portrait of Julia Gratiot, R.E. Lee's niece and wife of General Charles Gratiot.
      Weddings; Gratiot, Julia
    - Robert E. Lee to Col. Joseph G. Totten, 1847-10-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter regarding disbursement accounts in Mexico City. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Totten, Joseph Gilbert, 1788-1864
    - Robert E. Lee to Annie Carter Lee, 1848-02-29; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Details the transition from winter to spring in Mexico City. Compares the cats in Mexico City to those in his own home. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Lee, Annie Carter
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1850-09-19; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Letter concerning Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II's appointment at the United States Military Academy. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Only contains a photocopy and transcription of the letter. The original is believed to be located at the Maryland Historical Society. Please refer to them with any questions regarding conditions governing use.
      Bonaparte, Jérôme Napoléon, 1805-1870; Bonaparte, Jérôme Napoléon, 1830-1893
    - Robert E. Lee to Honorable C. M. Conrad, 1851-06-30; Recommendation of Sergeant McNally to the United States Military Academy. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Conrad, Charles Magill, 1804-1878
    - Robert E. Lee to Caroline Cora Peters, 1851-11-20; Concerns his upcoming visit to New York. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Peters (Benson), Caroline Cora
    - Robert E. Lee to Nat Burwell, 1852-01-05; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee apologizes for his late arrival. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      File consists of a copy of the letter. The location of the original is unknown.
      Burwell, Nat
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1852-02-06; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Short note concerning "Memoir on the U.S. Artillery" and family matters.
      Facsimile copy. Location of original unknown.
      Bonaparte, Jérôme Napoléon, 1805-1870
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1852-07-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee requests help from J.N. Bonaparte with delivery of clothing for his nephew Fitzhugh. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      File contains a facsimile of the original letter. Location of the original letter is unknown.
    - Robert E. Lee to Col. Joseph G. Totten, 1852-09-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee informs Totten that in obedience to instrusctions, he has relieved Captain Brewerton of the superintendency at the United States Military Academy. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Robert E. Lee to Im Jones, 1852-10-28; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee requests to be relieved from duty at the United States Military Academy. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Robert E. Lee to William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, 1853-03-03; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes to his son updating him on family matters and inquiring about his wrist. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1853-03-12; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee relates his experience as superintendent at West Point and comments on his superior's son, Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      This file only includes a photocopy of the letter. Please refer to the Maryland Historical Society with any questions concerning conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1853-03-19; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes of possible change of duty for Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      The file includes a photocopy of the letter. Original is housed by the Maryland Historical Society. Please refer to them with any questions regarding conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Jacob J. Fort Esq., 1953-03-29; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes to father of an ill student, detailing his ailment and present condition. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1853-04-11; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee discusses possible change of duty for Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Robert E. Lee to father of a student, 1853-04-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee discusses the academic performance of a student with his parent. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1853-05-11; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee comments on Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II's transfer. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Original copy is housed by the Maryland Historical Society. Please refer to them with any questions regarding conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Unknown Individual, 1854-03-29; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes a letter of recommendation for Mr. A.A. Bursley. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1854-05-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee wishes Bonaparte a good trip to France and laments his inability to join them. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      The original letter is housed by the Maryland Historical Society. Please contact them with any questions regarding the conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1854-11-04; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee comments on Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte II moving to France. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      The original document is housed by the Maryland Historical Society. Please contact them with any questions regarding the conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel Cooper, 1854-11-11; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee summons Lt. Jas. Thompson to appear before a court martial. (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Please note that we do not house the original document and are not aware of the conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1854-12-05; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 1, Folder 30)
      The original document is housed by the Maryland Historical Society. Please refer to them with any questions regarding the conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Jefferson Davis, 1855-02-28; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee recommends his son's promotion to lieutenant. (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Davis, Jefferson; Lee, William Henry Fitzhugh
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1855-02-28; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes of family and professional matters, including the dismissal of a young cadet for assaulting a fellow student. (Box 1, Folder 32)
      The original document is housed at the Maryland Historical Society. Please refer to them with any questions regarding the conditions governing use.
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel Cooper, 1855-03-17; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes a recommendation note for Harry Burgden. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel Cooper, 1855-05-12; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee requests extra funding for recruiting purposes. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      We only house a photocopy of the note. The location of the original document is unknown.
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel Cooper, 1855-05-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee comments on status of his men and supplies. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Robert E. Lee to Mrs. H. W. Barry, 1857; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee discusses social and family matters. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Robert E. Lee to Samuel Cooper, 1857-08-25; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee writes a letter of recommendation for John M. Jones. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Robert E. Lee to Jerome Napoleon Bonaparte, 1858-06-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee expresses excitement at the prospect of receiving a bust of Jerome N. Bonaparte. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Robert E. Lee to Irwin McDowell, 1858-07-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee updates the Major with his new address for the month of August. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Robert E. Lee to S. Thomas, 1859-01-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee reports his new address in Arlington, Virginia. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Robert E. Lee to S. Thomas, 1859-04-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee reports his new address for August in Arlington, Virginia. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Robert E. Lee to S. Thomas, 1859-05-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee informs Col. S. Thomas that his address for the month of May will be in Arlington, Virginia. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Robert E. Lee to S. Thomas, 1859-06-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee reports his address for the current month. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Robert E. Lee to S.. Thomas, 1859-06-16; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee thanks the Colonel for patience and permission to extend his leave of absence. He is occupied handling the will of Mr. Custis. (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Slavery; Slavery -- Emancipation
    - Robert E. Lee to S. Thomas, 1859-07-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee informs Thomas that he has received a four month extension for his leave of absence. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Robert E. Lee to Winfield Scott, 1861-04-20; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee resigns from the United States Army, attributing it to the necessity of protecting his home state. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      We do not house the original letter, only a photocopy. For conditions governing use, please refer to owner of the original piece.
      Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866
    - Robert E. Lee to Mr. Rutherford, 1861-04-29; Someone writes on the behalf of Lee, declining an invitation to dinner. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    - Robert E. Lee to Thomas H. Ellis, 1961-07-24; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee thanks Ellis for sending him books. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Robert E. Lee to Unknown Individual, 1861-10-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee approves a substitute for Private Epps. (Box 1, Folder 49)
      File includes two photostatic copies of small segments of text. The location of the original notes is unknown.
    - Robert E. Lee to Richard Caldwell, 1861-12-04; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee expresses gratitude for the bedding he and his received from the Soldiers Relief Association. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Robert E. Lee to W. J. Magrath Esq., 1862-02-28; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Robert E. Lee requests infrastructural and logistical accommodations for the movement of troops stationed along the line of the road and protection of Charleston and Savannah. (Box 1, Folder 51)